Guide to the John Knowles Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Knowles papers
1954-2000
YCAL MSS 725
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
22.67
(37 boxes) + 1 art object
The John Knowles Papers document the career and personal life of American author John Knowles between 1954 and 2000. The papers provide insight into Knowles's career as an author and consist of correspondence, writings, notebooks, scrapbooks, printed material, personal papers, audiovisual media, and other papers. The papers also include a portrait (pencil on paper) of Knowles by Don Bachardy. There is some material relating to Knowles's friendships with Truman Capote and Thornton Wilder. Various drafts of his writings, including A Separate Peace and its companion novel Peace Breaks Out, reflect Knowles's creative life.
Knowles, John, 1926-2001
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John Knowles (Yale 1949), 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 18 (audiocassettes, CD): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
John Knowles (1926-2001)
John Knowles was an American novelist best known for his first novel A Separate Peace.
Scope and Contents
The John Knowles Papers document the career and personal life of American author John Knowles between 1954 and 2000. The papers provide insight into Knowles's career as an author and consist of correspondence, writings, notebooks, scrapbooks, printed material, personal papers, audio-visual media, and other papers. The papers also include a portrait of Knowles by Don Bachardy. There is some material relating to Knowles's friendship with Truman Capote and Thornton Wilder. Various drafts of his writings, including A Separate Peace and its companion novel Peace Breaks Out, reflect Knowles's creative process.
Arrangement
Organized into one grouping: I. March 2002 Acquisition.
Sound recordings; Drawings (visual works); Bachardy, Don, 1934-; Capote, Truman, 1924-1984; Knowles, John, 1926-2001; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975
- March 2002 Acquisition, 1; 22.59; (36 boxes) + 1 art object
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains correspondence, writings, notebooks, scrapbooks, printed material, personal papers, audio-visual material, a framed portrait, and other papers by and relating to John Knowles.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 18 (audiocassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 396
  - Notebooks (Box 1)
  - Notebooks (Box 2)
  - Notebooks (Box 3)
  - Notebooks (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (Box 6)
  - The Private Life of Axie Reed: typescripts, circa 1986 (Box 7)
  - The Private Life of Axie Reed: typescripts, circa 1986 (Box 8)
  - A Vein of Riches: typescripts and drafts, circa 1978 (Box 9)
  - A Vein of Riches: typescripts and drafts, circa 1978 (Box 10)
  - A Separate Peace, adaptations; A Stolen Past; Peace Breaks Out, 1960s-1990s (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous writings, circa 1960 (Box 12)
    Learning and Teaching; Rapture of the Deep; A Special Time; a Special School; Intro to Collection of Short Stories; Worthy of the Sea; Hawthorne, an Introduction; The Interruption; The Yale Mystique; Egypt on the Brink of the Six Day War; and writings of others
  - Spreading Fires and other writings, 1970s-1980s (Box 13)
    Includes diaries and lecture notes; essays, stories, and fragments of various works
  - Miscellaneous writings and papers, 1970-1980s (Box 14)
    Diaries; reviews of Peace Breaks Out; essays and reviews by Knowles
  - Spreading Fires; Other Seas, Other Ships (Box 15)
    Includes miscellaneous other papers
  - A Stolen Past, 1974-1983 (Box 16)
    Includes clipping file "The Rockefeller Swindle"
  - Yale University Class of 1959, The American Century: Our Half (50th Reunion, 1999). Includes essay by Knowles: "Writing at Yale...And Beyond." (Box 17)
  - Audiovisual Materials of A Separate Peace, (16 audiocassettes, 1 CD) (Box 18)
    Fifteen of the audiocassettes are commercial. They have not been digitized.
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - A Separate Peace: Demo. Rec., undated; 1; 00:25:25 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002104613048)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 19 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbooks (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbooks (Box 21 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbooks (Box 22 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbooks (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbooks (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbooks (Box 25 (Oversize))
  - Spreading Fires (a novel), 1973-1974 (Box 26)
    Includes 6 notebooks containing notes and drafts; First draft, typescript, revised; Second draft, revised; Third draft, revised; Photocopy, with revisions; draft of letter to publisher from author, 1973 Oct 19
  - Descent to Proselito: 3 notebooks; typescript, circa 1955 (Box 27)
  - Indian Summer: 5 notebooks; typescript; revised pages, circa 1966 (Box 27)
  - Indian Summer: proofs, circa 1966 (Box 28)
  - Double Vision: Thoughts from Abroad: typescript; 18 notebooks, circa 1964 (Box 29)
  - Double Vision: Thoughts from Abroad: research notes, clippings and travel literature, circa 1964 (Box 30)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 30)
  - The Paragon: 7 notebooks; typescript; photocopy, circa 1971 (Box 30)
  - The Paragon: typescript, circa 1971 (Box 31)
  - Phineas: Six Stories: typescript; original and carbon; 4 proofs; related notes and other writings (Box 31)
  - Morning in Antibes: Ms.; typescript; 4 notebooks; French newspapers, circa 1962 (Box 32)
  - A Separate Peace: typescript, circa 1960 (Box 33)
  - Too Far to Walk (dramatic treatment): Notebook containing ms. and notes; Typescript (notes) (Box 33)
  - Page proof of John Hersey novel (Box 33)
  - 5 engagement calendars (Box 33)
  - 16 notebooks (Box 33)
  - Address book (Box 33)
  - Correspondence (Box 34)
  - Articles (Box 34)
    Short articles; Idea memos; An Anglo-American Dream; Book reviews; The Count in his Castle; Forquet; France; The Great City Comes to Virginia; Jack Knowles vacation; The Heart of France; How to be Sick Abroad; The Incomplete Skin Diver; The Last Monks of Byzantium; Natural America; News; Not Taking Things So Hard; Radicofani; Sweden; Thought for the Milestone Year; Wedding in Old France; The Young Writer's Enemies and Friends
  - Short stories (Box 34)
    The Cure; Delay en Route; Leaving Home; Night Music; Summer Street; Traffic Control on the Grand Canal
  - Articles and short stories (Box 35)
    The Reading of the Will; Publishers Weekly: press article; Paradises I have Known; Ohlik, Giza: School at the Frontier, review; The Heart of France; The Outer Islands of Hawaii; France Fumbles with the American Way; Crossing the Snow Bridge; The Anchor Man; Newsday columns; A Winter in Egypt and The Heart of France
  - Clippings (Box 35)
  - Periodicals (Box 35)
  - Packard, George V.: That Grail Song, Sam, One More Time, uncorrected proof (Box 35)
  - Printed material (Box 35)
  - Notebook (Box 35)
  - Passport (Box 35)
  - Clippings and periodicals (Box 36)
  - Framed portrait of John Knowles by Don Bachardy (Box 37 (ART))
  - "John Knowles - on Contemporary Fiction", Princeton University, event poster, 1968 April 3 (Box 38 (Oversize))